good let me try summing up what you've
said so far and you can tell me if i'm
full of shit or not or
uh or close or off which is that
the answer to the question of at least
an answer
a beginning answer to how game b could
beat game a
despite the fact that it's tiny today
and game a is huge and powerful
is that game a if it's crafted correctly
will do a better job of processing the
world
in a non-linear high complexity fashion
and even though it starts small
it will have a higher exponent and those
of us with a little bit of quantitative
background know
that over a long enough period of time
you can start mighty small and if you're
growing at a higher exponent you'll
eventually beat the big guy who's
growing at a lower
growing in a broader sense of solving
the world's problems
than than the bigger guy is that getting
something near the sense of what you
were trying to
uh communicate yep yeah that's pretty
much i think you may have started with
game a but
it became evident that you definitely
meant game b there and yes so that would
be that okay and this is particularly
the case
when this rate versus state trade-off
is so important you know so if you've
got a starting
gate where the the ability to be able to
do this innovation thing the raw
material
for doing the innovation the adjacent
apotheosis the phase space of
possibility is now
very very large and so the leverage of
increasing your capacity
to do innovation to to to move the
the adjacent possible is is very high
you know so
if we had tried to do this game b thing
in 1750
we couldn't have gotten there because
there wasn't enough stuff
in the space of possibility even if we
try to do in 1950 we couldn't have
gotten there
but but now we can't or at least at
least in principle it's possible that we
can
and so it's kind of this weird thing
where almost exactly the same
characteristic
that causes gaming to be so challenging
which is to say
accelerating change happens to be the
same exact characteristic
that drives the possibility of game b
and we can exactly say that the game b
is just
designed from the from the get go to be
substantially better at innovation
than game a and okay that's that's
actually kind of simple it's like okay
as we're trying to do we're trying to
figure out
how do we take a look at this thing
called creative collaboration
and how do we do that thing how do we
design something which is
just a whole lot better at creative
collaboration recognizing that
we're now in a place where escape
velocity
through the innovation vector is
available we might actually be able to
do something with just
so much better that it just lifts off
you know let's say that game a right now
has a million
power um and this is i'm just going to
read in numbers just re-articulate what
you just said
the game gaming has a million power and
its rate
of change is a hundred thousand per unit
time
and so next unit you know t plus one
it's 100 a million one
let's say game b right now is starting
out at 10 000 power
uh but its rate of change is actually
something like
compounding curve so it's not a hundred
thousand per unit time it's
1.1 times its current number
and so it's going to take a while for a
while 10 000 times
1.1 is not getting a lot bigger but
obviously if you just draw the curves
there is a crossover point and that
crossover point by the way is a
crossover point with wings
because you know you've crossed over and
within
a not very long time after you've
crossed over you've blown right past
and not very long time after that you've
actually gone so far past that it's not
even clear what the hell just happened
and we can actually be in some sense
even very concrete about this i think it
was
an sfi book but maybe it wasn't
i think it may have been the origin of
well and there was a conversation about
you know what it meant actually maybe it
was matt ridley's book
where they were talking about like to
have been louis xiv
and you know on the one hand to have
been louis the 14th
at his time frame had a was massively
massively better than just being an
average person
and on the other hand almost everybody
alive right now is better off than louis
xiv
the simple fact of say for example we
have toothbrushes and
obviously telecommunications
transportation air conditioning indoor
plumbing
antibiotics like fill in the blank and
you know the the rate of of innovation
compared to the state is one where we
have all
blown right by so if you imagine that
you had a choice the the louis louis xiv
was sitting there and he had a choice he
could either ride
train a where he gets to be louis the
14th and gets to be the top dog
but train a has a particular rate of
change
or he gets on train b and train b has a
characteristic where he no longer gets
to be louis the 14th he just has to be a
peer along with everybody else
but it has a different a faster rate of
change
he may be hard pressed to make that
choice he may be like man i really
prefer to be lou the 14th
but it's actually a better choice if you
like things like toothbrushes and
indoor plumbing and modern dentistry in
general whenever people talk about the
good old days i just say
modern dentistry right and of course
when i'm when i'm right now
a lot of the languaging is focused on
stuff like technology
like physical technology like modern
dentistry or toothbrushes
but in the context of game b what we
notice is that
a large amount of the innovation field
actually has to happen at the level
of people relationships
human beings innovation happening in the
domain
of how human beings are able to show up
in relationship with themselves with
each other and with nature
for the obvious reason that if you all
you do is run forward
at a faster pace along the technology
vector
you're just going to blow us up faster
so we have to actually do something and
this is okay this is one of the reasons
why
i at least spend a lot of time thinking
about it in terms of meta design and not
in terms of just engineering
if we're going to develop something
which is just a whole lot better at
creative collaboration
we actually notice from the very get-go
that we also have to design something
that is a whole lot better
at cultivating collective wisdom
that is at least symmetric with and
probably more superior to
the power that we're generating through
this creative collaboration
so like this is a meta design constraint
game b must must must orient its primary
innovation capacity
first and foremost towards cultivating
individual and collective sovereignty
which is to say
wisdom and maturity and a an awareness
of how choices actually show up in the
world
more than the rate at which it increases
individual collective power